<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Counsel to the husband: to the wife instruction A short and pithy treatise of seuerall and ioynt duties, belonging vnto man and wife, as counsels to the one, and instructions to the other; for their more perfect happinesse in this present life, and their eternall glorie in the life to come.</title>
            <author>Ste. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854048</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854048</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 575:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Counsel to the husband: to the wife instruction A short and pithy treatise of seuerall and ioynt duties, belonging vnto man and wife, as counsels to the one, and instructions to the other; for their more perfect happinesse in this present life, and their eternall glorie in the life to come.</title>
                  <author>Ste. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 97, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Richard Boyle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Ste. B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Religious aspects --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19454:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19454:1"/>
            <p>COVNSEL TO THE HVSBAND: TO THE WIFE Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>A SHORT AND PI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY TREATISE OF SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall and ioynt duties, belonging <hi>vnto man and wife, as counſels to the</hi> one, and inſtructions to the other; for their more perfect happineſſe in this preſent life, and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glorie in the life to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Richard Boyle.</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19454:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19454:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND my very Chriſtian friends, Maſter THOMAS GERVOYSE,</hi> and his vertuous wife Miſtris <hi>LVCY GER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOYSE,</hi> true happineſſe in this life, and eternall glorie in the life to come, be from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through Ieſus Christ.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y VVorſhipfull deare friends, in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dutie which I owe vnto your worſhipfull Parents, who haue a long
<pb facs="tcp:19454:3"/> time deſerued much at mine hands (and much more then I can repay) as alſo in the loue J beare to your owne and your beloued yok<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, bethinking with my ſelfe wherein to ſhew ſome token of this loue, (as it well becommeth and concerneth a thankefull heart) and weighing the estate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto God hath called you, of the marriage band, J did light vpon this argument, thinking it the fittest for your vſe, and the eaſieſt for my ſtudie to labour in, by
<pb facs="tcp:19454:3"/> reaſon of mine experience of the euils thereof: which, as a token of my loue, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the euill, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vnto the godly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and fruits of that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and honourable eſtate, J doe humbly preſent, and prefer vnto you: not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but you will both accept and apply it, as ſhall be moſt expedient in euery respect. And ſo to a ſlender worke, a ſhort and briefe Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may well ſuffice, that the porch of the houſe be not bigger then the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb facs="tcp:19454:4"/> And ſo I commend it to Gods glorie, and my ſelf to your ſeruice in the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all Chriſtian duty and ſeruice, <hi>Ste. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19454:4"/>
            <head>Counſell to the Huſband: To the wife inſtruction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole eſtate of mans happines, may eaſily bee diſpoſed, into the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two times; <hi>The ſtate of this life preſent: and the glorie of the life to come.</hi> This life being the firſt, is both the Image to reſemble, and the foundation, wherein to lay (or worke) that eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines. Neither is there any eſtate, wherein we may more liuely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, or ſenſiblie taſte and feele, any ſparckle or iot of the Lord our God, his eternall loue to vs, then in that vnited eſtate of man and wife; wherein two perſons
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19454:5"/> become but one,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.13.</note> which ſtill are two; and mutually owe to othe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeuerall dutie.<note place="margin">A double vnion.</note> The vnion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as it is vnſpeakeable (where there is (indeede) an holy vnion) ſo hath it pleaſed the Lord, not ſeldome, but often in his word, (and eſpecially in that <hi>Song of ſongs,</hi> called <hi>Salomons Canticles</hi>) vnder the title of an husband, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing with his wife, to ſet forth his loue vnto vs, what it is in Chriſt Ieſus. Whoſe mutuall kindnes, expreſſed (in that ſong I meane) in termes, in duties, in wanting each other, in ſeeking, in ſorrowing, in finding, in inioying, in ſolacing and imbracing, in vnwillingnes to leaue and depart each from other, may well ſhew the coniunction to be vnſpeakeable, betweene man and wife, (rightly conioyned, and yoked equally) and bee a liuely paterne of more heauenly things. Howbeit (I ſay) it is not in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, that this Image of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19454:5"/> happines doth appeare;<note place="margin">All mariages doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happines.</note> for in ſome, it beareth rather a type of helliſh ſorrowes, wherein (our Sauiour ſaith) ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.30.</note> when the iudgement ſhall bee pronounced vpon the reprobate <hi>[Goe away yee curſed ones into euerlaſting fire.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 41.</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, where the match is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete, the coniunction vnequall, the vnited in bodie, diſunited in ſpirit, of contrarie affections, harts and religions, duties vnperfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, each croſſing other, or any of the twaine vnwiſe that will not bee admoniſhed; what are the fruits there? but wrath, bitternes, contention, controlling, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, taking all things in the euill parte, ielouſie, vpbraiding, diſcontentment, falſe dealing, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret iuggling, conſpiring, wants, without pittying each other, toyle without helping each other; ſeeking each one his credit with diſcredit vnto both, with many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19454:6"/> other as grieuous to be ſpoken of as any paſt. All which (no doubt) made <hi>Salomon</hi> ſo to ſpeake,<note place="margin">Prou. 21.9.19.</note> as his Prouerbes doe beare witnes, namely, that it were better to dwell in the corner of an houſe top, yea in the wilderneſſe, moſt deſolate and ſolitarie: and as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, with dragons &amp; beares, or other cruell beaſts, then with the contentious and froward wife. So that (as I ſaid) this Image of Gods loue, and of our eternall and moſt happie coniunction with Chriſt, (he the head, and we the members; hee the husband, and we the wife; hee, our welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued one, and we his aſwell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) is not to bee found in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie coniunction (as wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence giueth cauſe of complaint to many) but onely in the godly vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted match; in the well ordered, and gouerned match.<note place="margin">A neceſſarie caueat.</note> So that, how neceſſarily doth it behooue them, that would liue perfectlie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19454:6"/> happie, (by inioying the one, and auoyding the other) to bee inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the meanes which leade hereunto? that is, ſeeing this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines is in the right ordering of man and wife themſelues, each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards other, and then both in the ioynt gouerning of their familie, to know (therefore) both their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall workes, and conioyned du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And whereas I called this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate before, a <hi>foundation,</hi> wherein to lay the worke of eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, I ſpake not without aduiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for that,<note place="margin">The Church is the ſchoole of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> as the Church (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) is the ſchoole of Gods kingdome, a place to make men fit, before they can enioy his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (vnderſtanding me of ſuch as come to the ſtate of diſcretion and iudgement) as alſo the word of God, is called the Goſpell of this kingdome, becauſe that in this life, it fitteth men thereunto; ſo is euery mans houſe, (rightlie ordered and gouerned by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19454:7"/> rules of godlines) not vniuſtly, or without cauſe (by the holy Ghoſt) called <hi>a Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.5. Reu. 1.6.</note> the Gouernours, Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets vnto God. Kings to rule, Prieſts to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice; and Prophets, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, or ſee inſtructed. The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band firſt and principally, as the head and high Prieſt; the wife in his abſence, or, as vpon iuſt cauſe, he ſhall require her: <hi>She openeth her mouth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) with wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30.26.</note> 
               <hi>and the Law of grace is in her tongue.</hi> So likewiſe did <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba</hi> teach her ſonne <hi>Salomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou. 30.</hi> See the title therof.</note> Leſt, whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The wife ſhall learne at home of her huſband,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.34. 1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> ſhe ſhould thinke her ſelfe abſolutely excuſed, or freed of this dutie. No, by no meanes may ſhee thinke it,<note place="margin">Vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men must teach in the familie.</note> as not being the meaneſt propertie of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife.</p>
            <p>In all which gouernment, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church oftentimes doth want the parts and members of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19454:7"/> her gouernment, by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, God is not ſo honoured, as he ſhould or might;<note place="margin">Godly houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders may haue perfect gouernment.</note> yet is it free to godly houſholders, to enioy this gouernment: for, how ſhould God want his orderly worſhip, morning &amp; euening, week-daies. Lords daies, bleſſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g and prayſing him, with ioy and comelines in a priuate familie, and in the time of the Goſpell? or how ſhould there want lawes, ordinances,<note place="margin">Euery godly familie, and well ordered, ſhould haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lawes for ſinne. <hi>Gen. 21.9. Gen. 37.41.</hi>
               </note> and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, againſt profaning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords day, ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, euill ſpeaking, quarrelling, ſtandring, vnchaſte ſpeaking, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> ſcoffing, or <hi>Eſaus</hi> threatning, where the Gouernors haue the authoritie to hold the ſterne, and command for God? except they want care and zeale, for Gods cauſes,<note place="margin">The chief cauſe why families doe abound in ſinne.</note> or hatred againſt ſinne, and regard onely to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues, and not how God is ſerued, worſhipped or obeyed. In all which conſideration, what a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19454:8"/> foundation of eternall happines is there laide, where there is ſuch an holy &amp; religious care to plant vertue, and ſupplant vice? to know the Lord, and to haue him ſerued aright?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.22.</note> whoſe ſeruice is freedome, and whatſoeuer free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome beſides, is but bondage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Satan.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note this.</note>Verily it is a great burthen, which gouernours of families doe beare, and their account is great; their families ſhould be churches, wherein God ſhould be hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſerued, and daily honoured: yea, they ſhould take care, that not only they themſelues feare God, (which yet is the leaſt care of too many) but their ſeruants alſo; that not onely they themſelues be not ſwearers, or exceſſiue perſons, but not any of their ſeruants bee knowne to be ſuch. A worthie preſident whereof is to be found in <hi>Dauids</hi> rule,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 101.</note> Pſalm. 101. which for his houſhold gouerment hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19454:8"/> propoſed vnto himſelfe, vowing vnto God, not onelie himſelfe to walke in the midſt of his houſe (that is) before all his familie) with an vpright heart, but that, ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, lyars,<note place="margin">A ſingular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders.</note> ſcorners and ſuch deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons, ſhould not dwell in his houſe; yea, hee would purge his houſe betimes (as one of the firſt workes that he would take in hand) to thruſt out all the workers of iniquitie from the citie of the Lord. And then, whom would he plant about him? euen ſuch as were nere <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.7. Pſalm. 101.6.</note> ſuch as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God, euen (as <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth them) the faithfull of the land, they ſhould dwell with him, who ſo walked in a perfect way hee ſhould ſerue him. A worthie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation it was vnto that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Captaine that he feared God with all his houſehold, that is, he kept none that outwardly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted not himſelfe vnto the comely order of his familie; none
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19454:9"/> that was to be attainted with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crimes, ſuch as the moſt mens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants are, and eſpecially Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and great perſonages,<note place="margin">In greateſt houſes moſt diſorder.</note> as i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had bidden battaile and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance vnto religion and religious order, retaining (in ſtead thereof) and maintaining withall, all ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and ſwaggering perſons, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and beaſtly ſwine, ſuch as may loathe an honeſt minde to come in companie withall; ſuch families are not Churches but ſtyes for ſwine; not congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Saints, but kennels for ſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling dogges; yea, euen very hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, for any manner nourture or true godlines, that is to bee found amongſt them. What will theſe doe when they ſhall come to account vnto God for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies?<note place="margin">Account for families, which we thinke not of.</note> or doe they not beleeue that they ſhall account for them? They, that know any thing, as they ſhould know, by the rule of Gods word, doe account it a great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19454:9"/> to take charge of a flocke, and to be Paſtor of a Church; and is not a familie then a great charge that is called a <hi>Church?</hi> Wee will ſay in an Engliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe,<note place="margin">A prouerb.</note> that there belongeth more to a marriage then two payre of bare legges; ſo we ſay further, that there belongeth more to a family then Gouernors, ſeruants, houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe, and prouiſion: there muſt be lawes and diſcipline, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and inſtruction, a watchman and ouerſeers, that all may walke vpright; that God being ſerued, hee may ſerue vs, and his name being daily bleſſed, he may bleſſe vs againe, and powre a bleſſing vpon our labours, which wee take in hand.</p>
            <p>Herehence then (my worthie, and worſhipfull friends) let mee deduce, for your vſe, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance theſe few, and ioynt duties to you and your bleſſed yokefel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to practiſe towards the Lord.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19454:10"/> Remember the words of <hi>Dauid</hi> before rehearſed; how timely hee would take in hand the religious ordering &amp; planting of his houſe. Forget not the words of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, who counſelleth you (and all that regard him for their Lord and Sauiour) firſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.33.</note> to ſeeke the kingdome of heauen and the righteouſnes thereof, and then (as it were without your care) all other things ſhould bee miniſtred vnto you. Let your gouernment and houſe, firſt entertaine Chriſt Ieſus (who neuer commeth emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie handed,<note place="margin">Chriſt neuer commeth emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie handed. <hi>Prou. 8.18.</hi>
               </note> but furniſhed with all grace and riches; euen durable riches (as <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth it) that is, the knowledge, the ſeruice and the true care of religious duties. Let God be aboue all things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in and of your ſelues, for example ſake, yea, for conſcience ſake, then of al, and euery ſeruant, men and maides, the chiefeſt, the baſeſt, ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they bee not profane
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19454:10"/> perſons as <hi>Eſau</hi> was,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.16.</note> who for a meſſe of pottage ſold his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, that is, ſuch as more eſteeme a meſſe of pottage, or a vaine toy, then the feare of the Lord, or to be taught any goodnes, or repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to leaue any euill. Keepe not that ſeruant who being attainted with any the aforeſaid crimes, of ſwearing, vncleannes,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15.16.</note> drunkennes or riot, and ſhall bee admoniſhed and conuicted thereof, according vnto due order of reproouing, which leaueth not his ſinne, and feareth not to ſinne, through contempt of order. That God, who commanded <hi>Abraham</hi> to caſt out <hi>Iſmael</hi> for his ſcoffing at <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.</note> commandeth you (and all Maſters) to caſt out the broode of <hi>Iſmael,</hi> (that is) all contemners, and reſiſters of religion.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.6.7.</note> They are the leauen, yea the very bane and poyſon, (let me ſpeake yet a little further,) a moſt grieuous plague and leaproſie, vnto any godly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19454:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> and honeſt familie.<note place="margin">Euill ſeruants are euer more offenſiue vnto the godlie.</note> Such doe not onely vexe the godly, if any be in it, but keepe away the godly, that would come vnto it. Let not therefore your family want neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie Lawes and penalties for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, whereby you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſinne, and be the meanes, if not of ſauing ſuch, as otherwiſe would periſh in ſinne, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God, yet, at the leaſt, of leſſening their torments in hel, by reſtraining the meaſure of their ſinne, according to which ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſoule be tormented.</p>
            <p>For want of godly diſcipline, how do ſerants, euen in the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of religious Gouernours, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, (may I not ſay abound?) in ſwearing ſcorning, &amp; moſt vile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour? I would I knew it not to be too true, in too many places of very religious account. Whoſe is the fault? verily y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gouernours: and they ſhall beare the ſinne of ſuch offenders. You will ſay, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19454:11"/> againſt ſwearing, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid their ſeruants; and they are taught the contrarie, neither take they their example from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors. All this is wel; but all this is not large enough for excuſe. I would to God al families had this to glorie of, the eaſier would be the reformation of the reſidue.</p>
            <p>All this while there is no mention of penall ſtatutes, dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall mulctes or puniſhments, corporall or pecuniarie, with cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and appointed watchmen and ouerſeers, for the ouerſight of the familie, and to wait vpon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, and obſerue the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the ſeruants; ſober, wiſe, and truſtie ſeruants, to whom au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, credit, and countenance may bee giuen to diſcharge this dutie thorowout the families. You will ſay, this were enough for a whole congregation. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, very true. And why not for euery honorable, worſhipfull, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19454:12"/> populous familie which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe account,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.5.</note> and call a Church? If it bee a Church, why ſhould it not haue the lawes and diſcipline of a Church? Indeede if it were ſo, ſinne muſt needes bee conſtrained to flee to the land of Shinar, Babylon, or confuſion, and would bee aſhamed to ſhew her head.<note place="margin">A reaſon why priuate fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies doe want good lawes.</note> Why then you will ſay, is it not ſo? Oh, we are aſhamed of the Goſpell: we feare to be euill ſpoken of, or that we ſhall not get ſeruants to do our worke and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines. Such pretences are coyned in the world, and we thinke them very reaſonable: but alas they are too narrow a couering to cloke or hide our falſe harted loue to Chriſt, our coldnes in religion, and our diſtruſt in God. Surelie I thinke it would thruſt out <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> with bottell and bag, (the bondwoman and her ſonne) ſwaggerers, royſters, and ruffian like ſeruants, with ſuch lewde and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19454:12"/> profane blaſphemers,<note place="margin">Act. 1.25.</note> as are more fit for hel (their owne inheritance, without repentance) then for godly families, which haue the name for religion. And as for the ſeruice of ſuch men, I cannot ſee how it ſhould be bleſſed, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed rather; nor how we ſhould doubt the hauing of religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, if we our ſelues (the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours) do truly loue religion, and would indeede haue ſuch, or none at all. But whiles wee haue ſuch linſie-wolſie mixtures,<note place="margin">Deut. 22.10.</note> an Oxe &amp; an Aſſe to draw together, one good and fiue euill, one that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth an oath, and halfe a doſen for one that ſhall make no bones of an oath, nay ſhall (it may bee) ſweare in contempt of ſuch a one, is it any meruaile, though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde good ſeruants? if our houſes were reformed (as they ought to be) like Gods houſe, and that Chriſt his gouernment did beare ſway therein, we ſhould not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19454:13"/> neede lay wait for ſuch ſeruants, they would enquire for vs, and ſue to be receiued as into the Arke of <hi>Noe?</hi> All this may be performed where there is not a Paſtor or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher reſident in the famile; but if there be no Paſtor in the publike congregation, you can by no meanes (well) want one in your familie. You will ſay, that is a great charge. I anſwere: nothing to the danger of the want of one. You know it is Gods ordinance to haue his word preached, and your familie inſtructed, as hath bin ſaid, &amp; none ſo fit and meet as by a godly Teacher. If you ſtick at the charge, then withall conſider whether you beſtow not as much, (if not oftentimes more) vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more vnneceſſary expenſes; as vpon vaine apparrell, vpon hawkes hounds, ſuperfluous or ſumptuous building, great houſekeeping, and ſuch like. I ſpeake not of playing or wicked gaming (becauſe I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19454:13"/> a Chriſtian Gentleman:) if you doe any of the former and want a Teacher, you ſet the carte before the horſe, and take the wrong courſe to thriue. If you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, and ſay, thoſe aforeſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes muſt needes be; I demand, before the meanes of ſaluation? What? Hawkes, or Hounds, or doſtly apparrell, or daintie fare, before the preaching of Gods word, his worſhip and ſeruice? <hi>Is it time</hi> (ſaith <hi>Haggaie) for your ſelues to dwell in ſeeled houſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1.4. Iob. 31.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and this Houſe lie waſte?</hi> As <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith; <hi>this were a wickednes and iniquitie to be condemned: yea,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this would bee a fire that ſhould deuoure to deſtruction, and roote out all his increaſe.</hi> For which, how Gods wrath came vpon that people; is in that chapter at large declared: the iudgements of God fell on them, in their eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and clothing, and earnings,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>[they put their wages into a broken
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19454:14"/> bagge].</hi> If yet you ſay, many neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting this religious care you ſpeake of, doe yet thriue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper; I anſwere, and many doe not: which doubtleſſe is Gods curſe vpon them. But, be they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons or gouernours, I ſay, the greater is Gods mercie, ſo to ſpare them in ſo manifeſt an offence againſt ſo holy a dutie: if they be others, (voide of religion) it is not to bee reſpected; whoſe thriuing is not a token of Gods loue vnto them, when they want grace to ſerue him rightly; and the more they thriue, &amp; yet right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerue him not, the greater will be their iudgement, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Let that be no preſident to you, againſt the plain euidence of the word of God, againſt which if a miracle,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1.2.3.4.5.</note> ſigne, or wonder may not preuaile, (which ſometimes to prooue men, God hath permitted and ſuffered) much leſſe may the thriuing of wicked men preuaile
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19454:14"/> in ſuch a caſe, vpon whom (if wee will reade the Scriptures) we ſhall ſee, God powreth his benefits, and filleth their bellies (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) with his hid treaſures,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 17.14.</note> much more then on the Godly, yea they haue no changes in their proſperous eſtate,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 55.19.</note> when the godly are afflicted and chaſtned euery morning, in bodie, goods, and good name. Therefore this is a ſlender ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke, and not worthie to be ſtucke at.<note place="margin">The charge of a Teacher coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruailed.</note> The charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of a reuerend and painefull Teacher (if any way your ſtate will beare it) doth bring his burthen of bleſſings other waies (if God be not vnrighteous) and till that charge bee defraied, certainely all our pleaſures, profits, and delights in whatſoeuer before named or may bee added vnto it, are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the vſe thereof, except wee be vnder the publicke miniſterie (as I ſaid before): for as in thoſe indifferent bleſſings (for ſo I may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19454:15"/> lawfullie cal them in a ſober vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,) there is ſome honeſt delight for gentle &amp; noble minds, ſo (yet) till the worſhip of God be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, they are vtterly vnlawful.</p>
            <p>If that bee therefore gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that to haue a Teacher bee needefull, the expence no heauie burthen, but vnwillingly endured; then, as my next counſell, ſee that your Teacher haue his due regard in his place and calling;<note place="margin">Teachers muſt haue their due regard in the family.</note> that is, ſee that hee haue meete reuerence with authoritie, both from your ſelues and all others in the family. For if he bee not regarded, how ſhall his word, his exhortation, or reproofe take place vnto Gods glorie? The Lord requireth for his workes ſake,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.12.13. 1. Tim. 5.17. Heb. 13.17.</note> that ſuch bee had in ſingular reuerence, in double honour, obeyed and ſubmitted vnto. All which is not as to his perſon, but to his office and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: not to him, but to Chriſt, whoſe word, perſon, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19454:15"/> he ſuſtaineth. The contempt of whom is likewiſe, not to him but to the Lord your Redeemer. When therefore in your familie, euery baſe perſon ſhall ſet him at naught, or being reprooued by him for any euill, ſhall ſcornfullie reſiſt, or reiect his counſell, what can this grow vnto, but an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them in their euills, and a diſcomfort vnto the Teacher to doe his dutie? Rightly to eſteeme Gods ſeruant, as the honour of his place &amp; calling doth require, muſt come from ſingular grace and knowledge of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and is not the weakeſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of a religious heart. Thus whiles you prouide for the true honour of your God (<note place="margin">Matth. 6.33.</note> as they that firſt ſeeke for the kingdome of GOD and his righteouſneſſe) you ſow vnto your owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for that they which honour God ſhall be honoured of God,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> his owne mouth hath witneſſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19454:16"/> it. Yea, in ſowing thus to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.8.</note> what fruit in your ſeaſon may you looke to reape, but that which is promiſed vnto godlines? which is, not onely the immortalitie of the life to come (which is of faith) but alſo Gods bleſſings in this preſent life, which is in ſight. <hi>Come children</hi> (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet) <hi>hearken vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 34.11.</note> 
               <hi>and I will teach you the feare of the Lord. What man is hee that deſireth life and would faine ſee good? Keepe thy tongue from euill and thy lippes that they ſpeake no guile, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hew euill and doe good, ſeeke peace and follow after it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the eies of the Lord are ouer the righteous, and his eares are open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their crie.</hi> Whereas on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ſide, what a foundation o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an vnhappie life, is in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and neglecters of religion? may they thinke to proſper? the Prophet ſaith the contrarie,<note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> that the countenance of the Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as feare not God, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19454:16"/> roote out their memoriall from off the earth.<note place="margin">The proſperitie of the wicked is accurſed.</note> Or admit they were outwardly bleſſed, what is their proſperitie, but accurſed vnto them, their table made a ſnare, and the things that ſhould be for their aduantage, an occaſion of falling? This ſhall ſuffice for the firſt point to direct you vnto religion and religious gouernment; and as the firſt ſteppe and beginning of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red happines;<note place="margin">Religion the ſalte of true happines. <hi>Tit. 1.15.</hi>
               </note> which (alſo) ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (as with ſalt) all other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of this lifes happines; for, if onely to the pure all things are pure, and onely they that ſo religiouſlie liue and gouerne (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods worde) are of God accounted pure,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.8.</note> and the pure onely bleſſed (as the mouth of all truth hath pronounced it:) and that on the contrarie, to them that are defiled and vnbeleeuing is nothing pure, but euen their minds and conſciences are defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then muſt it needes follow,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19454:17"/> that onely the religious inioy the bleſſings of God aright,<note place="margin">The vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate are but v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers vpon the gifts of God.</note> both of pleaſure and neceſſitie, all others being but vſurpers vpon the gifts of God.</p>
            <p>And admit, that for all this reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care, you ſhall ſuffer ſome reproach,<note place="margin">Reproach for Religion.</note> (as very aſſuredly it will follow from Satan &amp; his impes:) what of this? Yet is this directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods ſimple truth, &amp; the high way vnto happines. Yea, it is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more vndoubted truth, for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of truth muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſpoken of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Pet. 2.2. 2. Tim. 2.12.</hi> The Croſſe the ſhadow of the truth.</note> neither can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe be auoided, as the ſhadow of the truth. For which, if you ſhall bee diſcouraged, you will prooue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of Chriſts glorie, neither can you raigne as a partaker in happines,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.17.</note> except you ſuffer in this life, as a man moſt vnhappie. If you denie God;<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> he will deny you; if you walke with him, and be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, he will bee to you God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient: If you rule for God,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19454:17"/> and according to his word, then ſhall you rule with God, and ſit vpon his throne of eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Now what is the rule, that you muſt rule by? Is it the example of men, mighty, or multitude? No, by no meanes; for that is the certaine rule to erre by. I thank thee (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſaith our Sauior Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> Lord of heauen and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the prudent and wiſe, &amp; haſt reuealed them to babes and ſucklings. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.26.27.</note> that the calling and ſtate of true Chriſtianitie, is not compoſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Noble, learned, rich, or migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the world, but Gods choyce is quite againſt the reaſon of man, as to take fooliſh things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found wiſe (which through God it ſhal do eaſily) and weake things to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found mightie, &amp; vile things of the world, and things that are deſpiſed, &amp; things which are not, to bring to nought,<note place="margin">Gods manner of working.</note> things that are. This is Gods kind of working;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19454:18"/> and except you conſider it both well and eaſily, you ſhall ſtumble at it and be offended.</p>
            <p>The rule that you muſt leuel by (both concerning your ſelfe and others that ſhal be your charge) is the moſt bleſſed word of God; a young ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s rule;<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.</note> an old mans rule; euery mans rule: The Prince muſt rule by it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiect obey by it: the husband muſt gouerne his wife by it; the wife muſt yeeld her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection thereby as it preſcribeth. In it there is for euery condition, ſtate and degree, moſt perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to bee taught and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: then muſt you be diligent, herein:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.2. &amp; 119.55.62.148.</note> day and night did <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtudie therein, whence his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome came. If you take little paines in it, you muſt looke but for little wiſedome by it;<note place="margin">VVe muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement vnto our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> you muſt not looke to reape that you doe not ſow; nor thinke to ſow in vaine, where God ſaith you ſhal reape. If you ſpend more time in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19454:18"/> pleaſure and vanitie, you muſt looke for your great fruit and gaine in vanitie. If you loue and delight more in worldlie things then in ſpirituall, you muſt count vpon the reward accordingly. It is not poſſible to be attained, the pleaſure and glorie of this life, and the kingdome of heauen:<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> The ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>Diues</hi> &amp; <hi>Lazarus</hi> will teach you that moſt plainely: <hi>Diues</hi> had here his pleaſure, and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his paine; but <hi>Diues</hi> for his pleaſure exchanged torments, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> his afflictions were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into heauens ioyes. The ſtate of godlines is to ſuffer:<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> the ſtate of Chriſtianitie, is to be crucified with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 16.24</note> the members muſt be like their head; and hee that will bee Chriſts diſciple muſt forſake himſelfe, take vp the croſſe and follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And albeit I ſaid before, that the wiſe, noble, rich, and mightie, were not to be your rule, (becauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19454:19"/> Gods word doth onelie challenge that peculiar honour) yet ſaid I not, that amongſt theſe degrees, you ſhould finde no examples to behold and imitate.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> therefore ſaid, <hi>Not many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not many wiſe,</hi> &amp;c. he did not ſay none of theſe degrees, as none of the Nobles, wiſe and learned of the world, are called and ſtand for Chriſt; but not many of theſe. Some therefore both haue been, and in all ages ſhall bee called, that for nobilitie ſhall equall any; and for riches any; and for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ioyne with any, and yet true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſe Chriſt Ieſus. Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Herod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 8.3. Phli. 4.22. Act. 17.11.</note> as his ſtewards wife: ſome in <hi>Neros</hi> familie; ſome No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Berea; ſome Phariſies, ſome Counſellers,<note place="margin">Matth. 27.57.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea,</hi> a good man and a iuſt, with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and others; but all theſe did ſubmit their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, nobilitie, and learning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſcepter of Ieſus Chriſt, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19454:19"/> were content to be taught by him, what true wiſedome is;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to know nothing but Chriſt crucified,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> wiſhing God to forbid that hee ſhould reioyce in any thing but in Chriſt Ieſus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, by whom the world decai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, and he vnto the world. What ſhall I ſay vnto that cloud of witneſſes, <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ham, Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Moſes</hi> and the reſt, that are muſtered in that chapter?<note place="margin">Chap. 12.2.</note> all which endured with Chriſt the croſſe and deſpiſed the worlds ſhame, for their religious, vpright, and moſt holie life,<note place="margin">Chap. 11.38.</note> being perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and hated, of whom (yet) the world was not worthie; and whom (though we now honour) yet did the men of their time moſt grieuouſlie hate and diſdaine, as they doe any of the godly in this preſent age. Inſomuch, that though many who now ſpeake euill of the way of truth and the ſincere profeſſion of the Goſpell,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19454:20"/> would ſay with the Phariſies,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.30.</note> that if they had liued in their daies they would not haue been part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with them in their blood, nor ioyned with their perſecutors in their reprochfull doings: yet, if the caſe were ſo, and that they might now liue againe amongſt them to reprooue their wicked waies, and doe contrarie to their doings; they would no more ſpare them, then the godly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Elſe, why doe they ſo ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them, that follow their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſteppes? Or for what is it, that they that liue godly, are ſo repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but for their preciſe care vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duties of godlines? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what is the cauſe they are reproched, and branded with termes of (ſupppoſed) diſgrace? why? forſooth there is nothing (ſaith the profane ſcoffer) but preaching and praying and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines that they account of. If you come in their companie, beware
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19454:20"/> how you ſweare an oath: for if you doe, you ſhall bee ſure to heare of it, before your word be cold. They forſooth will neither ſit downe to meate, nor riſe from table, but they muſt haue grace, or it is worth nothing. And they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low nothing to be done vpon the Sonday, (which they cal the Lords day, and they ſay, it is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture name,) but what muſt be for neceſſitie, nor that neither if they could chuſe. They liue not like other Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which yet keepe as good houſes, as they doe; yea, with good ſport at Chriſtmas, with piping and dancing, and carding,<note place="margin">The worlds mirth.</note> and other Chriſtmas gambols, that men may be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie when they come: with them there is no ſuch good fellowſhip nor merriments, but all ſadnes, and ſcripture-talke, ſinging of Pſalmes, and reading of chapters, out of S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and I know not whence, nor what to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19454:21"/> make of ſuch a life, which was not ſeene in our forefathers daies till they came vp; enough to make one both weary and mad (I think) that is not vſed vnto it.</p>
            <p>Loe here this is the reproch of religion, and the cauſe thereof. That if you wilt not runne with the world into the madnes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.4.</note> and profane courſe thereof, neither be carnally minded with them, nor follow, nor faſhion your ſelfe in all vanitie like vnto them, you are ſtraightway mad and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; and (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) therefore ſpeake they euill, yea (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſaith) all manner of euill falſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly and vniuſtlie; and that for the things which God highlie commandeth vs,<note place="margin">Diſgrace for the things God moſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</note> men ſhall bee in moſt diſgrace with worldly men. But as S. <hi>Peter</hi> further ſaith, they ſhall giue their acccounts for ſuch vngodly ſpeaking, to him that is readie to iudge both the quicke and dead at his next appearing.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19454:21"/> This therefore muſt in no wiſe diſcourage you, or either of you, out as you haue thoſe worthie lightes, of both Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtels, yea, of Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, the chiefe corner ſtone, with all his godly traine the hundred fortie foure thouſand that ſtand with him vpon Mount Sion,<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 123.3.</note> who haue ſuffered (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) too much contempt, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſaid:) So might I (with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle)<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.5.</note> referre you to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of your moſt worthy and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipfull Parents (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Timothie,</hi> with <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunice,</hi> his mother and grande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother) who, in theſe verie ſame reproches, haue honoured and ſerued the Lord before you. If therefore the actions of our Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors doe ſo much delight vs, and are ſuch a ſpurre to incite and quicken vs in common virtues, how much more to imbrace god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and holie gouernment? And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19454:22"/> if the parents of our earthlie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall preuaile ſo with vs, how much rather the Parents of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happines, euen the father of Spirits (<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note>as the Apoſtle ſaith) ſhould he preuaile in his example of holines,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. Matth. 5.48.</note> who thus ſaith, <hi>Bee yee holy, as I am holy: Bee yee perfect, as your heauenly father is perfect? And if</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) ye call him fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>who without reſpect of perſons iudgeth according to euery mans workes, paſſe the time of your dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here in feare.</hi> All which, I haue the more ſpecially obſerued and touched,<note place="margin">A ſtumbling blocke remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> that I might remooue a ſtumbling blocke out of your way. For that many, who doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue the beſt things, haue yet no courage at all to practiſe them, becauſe of the croſſe; profeſſing (in a ſorte) they know the trueth, but doe (indeed) denie the power therof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit. 1.16.</hi> The power of profeſſion is in practiſe.</note> Which power ſtandeth not in knowledge alone, but in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and daily practiſe, with obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19454:22"/> to the trueth. And much more eaſie will it be for ſuch as doe not know the will of God, and therefore doe not obey his will, then for ſuch as know, and doe it not; many ſtripes belong vnto them, as our Sauiour ſaith. Whereunto I meane not, but to point with my finger (as it were) that you may bee armed to reſiſt ſuch ſpirituall cowardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt his trueth, if for your godly life,<note place="margin">Spirituall cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardlines.</note> and religious gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, you ſhal beare reproch: reioyce and bee glad thereof, and lay it vpon your ſhoulder (as <hi>Iob</hi> did,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.11.12. Iob. 31.35.36.</note> or would haue done his aduerſaries booke) and it ſhall become your crowne of glorie in the day of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>To proceede therefore (and yet briefly withal to go thorow the ſumme of this my ſlender pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) this is (but yet) the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of preſent and future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19454:23"/> There muſt bee f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the work and gouernment of a familie.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> For as the ſweetnes of muſicke conſiſteth in the orderlie concent and tuning of the ſtrings, without which bee hee neuer ſo skilfull that plaieth, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment neuer ſo good, the ſtrings neuer ſo true, there will bee no ſound of muſicke: euen ſo, if the ſtringes and members of a familie be ſet in tune, euery ſtring in his due and proper place, euery ſtring in his place keeping his note and height,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 133.</note> then (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) is there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> comelines, goodnes, and well agreement, which he reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to Hermons pleaſant and pretious dewes,<note place="margin">Verſ. 2.3.</note> with that moſt ſweet and ſacred ſauour, which from the Prieſtly anointing of <hi>Aaron</hi> did ariſe and ſmell. To this (naturally) we are not (by birth) apte; no more then the ſtrings of an inſtrument will of their owne nature without art or skill, fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19454:23"/> tune. Nay, by nature, wee are peruer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of all good order, and mean<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of good concent. Would ſubiects be vnder one head or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, if feare or grace did not compell them? hath not nature ſhewed her rebellion in children againſt their parents? Let onelie <hi>Abſolons</hi> ſtorie bee remembred.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> Hath not families bin ſubuerted, troubled and diſordered by hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ruling wickedlie, or the wiues rebelling diſobedientlie?<note place="margin">Gen. 4.23.</note> Let <hi>Lamech</hi> be an inſtance for the husbands fault,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> and <hi>Euah</hi> for the wife. Whereupon moſt iuſtly they were put vnder tribute, and muſt not be permitted to vſurpe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2 22.</note> I neede inſiſte in no other degrees and ſocieties (as I might, between the Paſtor and his flocke, (between whom and them whiles the people are as they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Prieſt (as <hi>Hoſeas</hi> ſaith)<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.4.</note> and will not follow him, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and ruling them from the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19454:24"/> Lord, how can there be harmonie without confuſion to the people to be lulled in their ſinnes?) It is ſufficient that wee haue examples for my preſent purpoſe. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it bee not from nature but from grace, and (as before was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) Gods word do contain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for al degrees and ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men, who can bee exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or diſpenced with to neglect that rule that deſireth a quiet and godly life, or would be held guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of contrarie cauſe?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A familie like to a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note>A familie may bee compared vnto a commonwealth: wherein, there are diuers ſocieties and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, reciprocally relating, and mutually depending one vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. The higheſt degree or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie is between the husband and the wife;<note place="margin">Simile.</note> and this is as the firſt wheele of a clocke, that turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout all the reſt in order. The next ſocietie, is betweene the Parents and the children. The third be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19454:24"/> the ſeruants one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and towards all other ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors in the familie.<note place="margin">Three ſocieties of a familie.</note> Into theſe three ſocieties may a familie bee diſpoſed. As touching the firſt and principall ſocietie (wherein alſo principally I purpoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte) which is betweene your ſelfe and your louing <hi>Hinde</hi> or <hi>Roe,</hi> whom many a time I haue bleſſed and ſhall bleſſe (by Gods grace) vnto your vſe and comfort) giue me leaue, (as one that can ſpeake by the ſureſt learning) to powre forth my minde mutually to you both; who can tell you, that the Canker vnto happines, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of confuſion to a familie, is the contention and diſagreement of man and wife.</p>
            <p>You will ſay,<note place="margin">The meanes to auoide conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie eaſie.</note> how may this be auoided? I anſwere, verie eaſilie, if in time true regard be had vnto mutual duty, without which there can be no comfort, nor that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of happines which before we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19454:25"/> ſpake of. Nay, (which is more,) to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſing of God, which is the foundation and cauſe of all happines.<note place="margin">Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance muſt bee preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnmeete conditions of peace.</note> It ſtandeth not in what man and wife ſhal conclude vpon, that there may be peace &amp; quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but what order God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them, to bee obeyed in their places: ſo that they muſt looke vnto Gods wiſedom, order, &amp; polity for oeconomical gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not what may ſeeme right and good in their owne eies. And that,<note place="margin">Deut. 22.5.</note> if the man may not weare womans apparrell, nor the woman mans, how much leſſe may the one vſurpe the others dignitie, or the other (to wit the husband) reſigne or giue ouer his ſoueraigntie vnto his wife? but each muſt keepe their place, their order, and heauenly politie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God hath called them. The husband is made the head,<note place="margin">The husband the head, the wife the bodie. <hi>1. Cor. 11.3.</hi>
               </note> and the wife reſembled to the bodie: May the head of a bodie (naturall)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19454:25"/> bee turned downeward? can the whole perſon ſo continue, &amp; liue well in that ſtate? how vnſeemelie is it? no more can the bodie poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique bee in peaceable or bleſſed condition, if order be inuerted. A moſt monſtrous thing it was that the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> complained of when he ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſay 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Children are extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners of my people, and women rule ouer them.</hi> You wil ſay the Prophet ſpeaketh of another caſe: I know it well: yet doth it (and very well may it) ſerue,<note place="margin">VVhich is, vvhen men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effeminate, are led (as vvas Ahab, and ſuch like) to prouoke the Lord.</note> in any caſe that is contrarie to Gods word to ſhew deformitie; but in his right caſe moſt notoriouſlie.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, ſhall the wife haue no gouernment? ſhall ſhe do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but be idle in the familie? I anſwere, my wordes yet tend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to no ſuch thing. Then, why was ſhe taken for a yokefellow? why is her helpe required,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> and ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an helper? Nay, I will ſay more, a glorious ſpectacle it may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19454:26"/> be, where the wife hath the whole gouernment. But with theſe cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that is, where the wife ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageth houſhould affaires, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently foreſeeing, carefully diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and religiouſlie gouerning to the honour of her husband.<note place="margin">Prou. 31.31.</note> Elſe would not <hi>Salomon</hi> haue ſaid (in the deſcription of a virtuous wife) <hi>Giue her the fruit of her hands, and let her owne workes praiſe her in the gates.</hi> Hauing before ſo notablie ſet forth the qualities of a virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wife: Firſt of her grace and obedient faithfulnes, <hi>ſhee will doe him good</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) though I know the wordes of his mother <hi>Bathſheba) and not euill all the daies of her life;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> no meruaile though hee ſaid,<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> her price was aboue the pearles: (marke yee wiues the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of a wife; and yee husbands (that are to chooſe) learne yee to chooſe a wife:) ſhe will doe him good; <hi>[good]</hi> ſhall be the obiect and ſubiect of her labour; ſo (you
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19454:26"/> will ſay) will many;<note place="margin">A perfect good.</note> but (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhe will doe him good, and not euill,</hi> that is, good without intermixing it with euill, good whollie; good abſolutely, good and no euill with it, to diſtaine or corrupt it. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol</hi> did ſome good when ſhee conuaied away <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.12.</note> when the houſe was beſet, and his life in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard;<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.20.</note> but how ill beſeeming was her euill ſcoffing at him, when his zeale in Gods cauſe did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and ſhew it ſelfe? Manie there are that will doe good vnto their husbands,<note place="margin">Many cauſes why women may doe good vnto their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and yet miſſe the right cauſe.</note> for diuers cauſes, nature will enforce, ſelfe vnitie and ioynt partaking in condition, conſtraine; deſert procure and euince; and many others. But to doe ſuch good, ſo ſoundely, ſo carefully, and that all the life long, as ſhall be voide of euill, how rare is ſuch a wife? Surely, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the multitude of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, (whereof ſome will doe but little good for much euill; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19454:27"/> ſome all euill and no good, ſuch as <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribeth in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs,<note place="margin">Prou. 12.4.</note> which by diſhonouring of her husband becommeth corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his bones) I ſay in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the multitude of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and fooliſh wiues which neither doe good to their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands nor to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ſuch virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ones may be ſaid to be rare &amp; ſcarce: yet otherwiſe I could point vnto ſome virtuous paternes (by coniunction neere vnto you; and the taſte whereof, if nature diuerte not, or grace (rather) faile not, you may finde in due time,) in whom ſhall ſhine a gratious meaſure of this heauenly virtue. But if by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of qualitie you would haue mee rather ſpeake, and for modeſty to inſiſt, asking me where ſhe is, or who may be found to be ſuch a wife: I will make this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſhe that indeuoureth (as in that aforeſaid deſcription <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> purtayeth it) ſhe that labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19454:27"/> in her place for her husbands quiet, for his health, for his credit, for his wealth, for his happines in his eſtate more then for her ſelfe, and counteth his in all thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects her owne: this is ſhee, that doth her husband good,<note place="margin">The wiues will and deſire to do her husband good and not euill, is her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note> and not euil; if withall ſhe abide herein all the daies of her life. It is indeede the will, indeuour, and faithfull practiſe, that is this perfection, (for other, in any of our duties ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards God, or man, cannot be attained vnto) which here is ſpoken of: whereunto whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhee bee that indeauoureth, is that virtuous wife.</p>
            <p>Which point (to returne again) being poſitiuely (as a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſet downe by <hi>Salomon,</hi> he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the reſt, her labour how painefull, her skill how excellent, her wiſedom how incomparable, her religion how ſincere; <hi>She ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her mouth with wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and the Law of grace is in her tongue;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19454:28"/> She ouerſeeth the way of her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> (Loe her gouernment.) <hi>&amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the bread of Idlenes: her children riſe vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 28. Verſ. 29.</note> 
               <hi>and call her bleſſed; her huſband alſo ſhall praiſe her, ſaying, many daughters haue done virtuouſlie, but thou ſurmounteſt them all,</hi> &amp;c. So that it was not for nought, that before I ſaid it might be a glorious ſpectacle, to ſee the wife ſuſtaine the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould gouernment and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the affaires pertaining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Where I meant not euery wife, the fooliſh and vnprofitable wife, the corruption of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands bones and diſhonour of his life,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.18.</note> which becommeth an hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his aduerſaries and the vile to plough withall; but (as I ſaid) with reſpect of theſe cautions: 1. That the wife be fit for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſhe vndertaketh. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer ſo fit, with the conſent and refere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of her husbands wil, taking all her light (as the Moone
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19454:28"/> is ſaid from the Sunne, ſo ſhe) from her husband, for gouernment and authoritie,<note place="margin">The wife the husbands lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant.</note> as his Lieutenant vnder him; and ſo wiſely diſpoſing all to his honour accordinglie. In ſuch a caſe,<note place="margin">The wife go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning well becommeth an honour vnto the husband.</note> how great an honour is the wiues godly gouernment vnto the husband? whiles hee as king to command, yet with loue as an husband, ſhall goe in and out, in the middeſt of his familie? not fearing ſpoyle, whether he be at home or abroade; nor needing vnlawfull ſpoyles to maintaine his ſtate. As alſo, how honourable a ſeruice is it in the wife, to depend vpon his becke? to aduiſe with her head? to leane vpon his breſt? and yet to haue the authoritie to doe what ſhe will? that is, whileſt her will is honeſt, lawfull, and to her husbands good, as hath been ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Can this be counted ſlauerie, or ſeruill ſubiection? muſt there not be in ſome ſubiection? Can al (in a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19454:29"/> nation bee kings? Can all in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily bee fathers? can all be wiues? can all bee euery thing? <hi>If the whole bodie</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>were an <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.17.</note> 
               <hi>where were the hearing? or if all were the eare, where were the ſmelling?</hi> If therfore in a kingdom, or familie, there muſt of neceſſitie be theſe degrees, and that wee ſee men ſo ſubiect to Princes, that they contentedly delight therein, and neither cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it ſlauiſhnes, nor affect aboue their ſtate (though ſome wicked doe otherwiſe) ſhould not the wife look vnto the hand of God,<note place="margin">The vvife muſt conſider that it is God, vvho hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned her vnto her ſubiection.</note> which made her the wife, and not the husband, the weaker veſſell, and not the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? the bodie, and not the head? to obey, and not to rule? that is, not to rule without obedience. To grudge hereat, is not againſt the husband, but againſt God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: to gouerne otherwiſe, is not to rule, but to vſurpe. Therefore, the Apoſtle ſaid not, the wife ſhal not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19454:29"/> rule, but he ſaid:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>I permit not a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to teach, nor to vſurpe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer the man.</hi> That is (as vnder correction I take it) without the husbandes conſent, will, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; neither conſtrained by her ſhrewdnes, but referred for cauſe (voluntarilie) to exerciſe the rule and gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the family. And this is that I ſaid, or meant before, which communicablie the husband may not diſpoſe to the wife, though he tranſlate the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of things; namely, the honor of Headſhip, to alter, order and direct, as in wiſedome hee ſeeth cauſe: which glorie muſt ſtill ſhine in his face, as he liueth in his familie, and not in hers in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; he muſt ſtill be ſeene to bee the head and husband, and ſhee may not beare it; which were moſt vncomely, yea, her very ſhame and diſhonour, if ſhee waigh it rightlie.</p>
            <p>Now contrarie to all this, one
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19454:30"/> euil ſicknes I haue obſerued in the experience of my daies,<note place="margin">An euill obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued amongſt men and their wiues.</note> (to ſpeake according to the phraſe of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) which I find not the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders therein carefully to preuent, though it be the confuſion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage happines: namely, where the husband and the wife are at oddes, which of them ſhall firſt begin to performe their duty, that is,<note place="margin">A law point betweene man and wife.</note> whether the husbands loue bee the foundation of the wiues obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; or the wiues obedience of the husbands loue. The wife will ſay, Let mine husband loue me as he ſhould, and I will obey him as I ought. The busband he ſaith, Let her doe her dutie, and I will loue and maintaine her. Thus they ſtand at ſtaues end, both of them agreeing in generall, that ioynt dutie is to be performed of both, but neither at agreement which ſhall begin.</p>
            <p>Surely, as in all duties, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles counſell is,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.10.</note> that in giuing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19454:30"/> honour one ſhould goe before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that is, euery member ſhould ſtriue to giue each other the chiefeſt honour (a note of true loue, and ſingular humilitie:) ſo could I wiſh that it might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer grow to queſtion of law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and wife whoſe is the dutie (for foundation) to begin the worke of houſehold gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but for them rather to ſtriue,<note place="margin">VVhat ſhould be, not vvhat is.</note> who ſhould bee moſt carefull of each others good. The husband (in needfull ſeruice) ſhould not neede to ſay, Good wife helpe me herein (I meane in things euident vnto her) but the wife ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent him with, Good husband let me doe it for you. Neither the wife to ſay (in like caſe) I pray hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band doe this for me; but hee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take care to preuent her deſire.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.23.24</note> Elſe what meaneth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle by thoſe words, which of this eſtate hee vttereth; <hi>The wife careth for the things of the world,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19454:31"/> how ſhe may pleaſe her huſband?</hi> And againe: <hi>The huſband careth for the things of this world, how hee may pleaſe his wife.</hi> Thus they ſhould not ſtriue, vnleſſe it were to giue honour (as was ſaid) and to doe ſeruice, and by loue to preuent each other, in that which loue ſhould further one another in, to the benefit of the whole, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Lord. And ſurely where true loue raigneth indeede, and not a counterfeit ſhew of loue; or where (in faithfull loue,) either of them are truely carefull of each others good, they ſhall not neede to ſue each other at the law for their right, or complaine they haue wrong; but as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Let there bee no ſtrife (I pray thee) betweene thee and me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But if thou wilt take the left hand, then I will goe to the right; or if thou wilt goe to the right, I will take the left:</hi> ſo quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would they compound, nay
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19454:31"/> make no queſtion thereof.</p>
            <p>But if there bee ſuch,<note place="margin">The remedie of the foreſaid euill ſicknes.</note> as cannot end this controuerſie without the Law, (as no queſtion there bee of both, vnreaſonable men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) men that will rule (like <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech</hi>) tyrannouſlie, and women that will liue contentiouſlie, to whom the wiues will ſay: If my husband will loue me I will obey him; and ſuch men ſay, If my wife will ſerue me, I wil be beneuolent: then this I muſt ſay,<note place="margin">A doome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wife that conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</note> The wrong and burthen will light vpon the womans backe. By wrong I meane not iniuſtice, but as we ſay in our prouerbe, the wrong end of the ſtaffe will be her parte; that is, it is in vaine (in this caſe) for the wife to ſtriue with the husband, which is, the weaker with the ſtronger; the horſe (pardon mee good wiues to vſe ſo baſe a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude) the horſe (I ſay) with him that hath the bridle and is able to ſit faſt.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19454:32"/>
            <p>Concerning which point, if women will bring their caſe to the Law of Gods word (which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt rule them here, or elſe will rule and iudge them, moſt fearefully elſewhere) they ſhall finde,<note place="margin">Reaſons vvhy the husband ought to be ſuperiour, and the vvife to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey firſt. <hi>1. Tim. 2.13.</hi>
               </note> firſt the man to haue the prerogatiue by theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: 1. By being called the head, ſhe the bodie. 2. The man to be firſt created, and ſo perfect (tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching creation) without her; though in regard of fellowſhip, and procreation (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>Neither is the man without the woman, nor the woman without the man in the Lord:</hi> and therefore hee ſaith, that the man was not made for the woman, but the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for the man.<note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Adam and Eue for ſinne.</note> 3. As the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (being the weaker veſſell) was deceiued by the diuell, and ſo deceiued man; ſo God (calling them both before his iudgement ſeate) arraigned,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> accuſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned both of them, for their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19454:32"/> fault and ſinne:<note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> The man (for his looſenes of gouernment in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his wife) was condemned (not to loſe his gouernment, but) to labour and paine, to trauaile with paine for foode and maintenance: The woman, beſides her peculiar paines ioyned with his generall,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.15.</note> (wherein yet, being patient, ſhee ſerueth God, as an excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and handmaide, to ſtore and fulfill his kingdome) I ſay, beſides theſe ioynt or peculiar paines (as to the principall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cauſe of <hi>Adams</hi> miſerie, for that ſhe did that, which Satan otherwiſe could not haue done without her) the Lord ouer and aboue condemneth her (for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute) of all obedience to her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,<note place="margin">The vviues tribute to the husband. <hi>Verſ. 16.</hi>
               </note> ſaying: <hi>Thy deſire ſhall bee ſubiect to thine husband, and hee ſhall rule ouer thee:</hi> which words, being ſo plaine and euident, need no expoſition in the world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neede I to confirme it with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19454:33"/> many teſtimonies, which abound in the Scriptures to this effect and purpoſe.<note place="margin">The ſentence muſt needes be iuſt and good vvhen God is the Iudge.</note> So that the Lord (not man) decideth this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, and ſubiecteth the wife, both in deſire and will vnto her husband, telling them, who ſhall begin, who ſhall lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and how the worke and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall ariſe thereon. Thus, and thus (ſaith God) it ſhall be; both deſire [to haue] euen deſire of good things, and of all things; and will, [or power] to doe or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ought, both theſe (ſaith God) ſhall bee ſubiect to thine husband, and hee ſhall rule ouer thee.</p>
            <p>Hearken now (my deere friend) here, vnto the iudgement of the Lord, though I truſt I ſhall haue little cauſe to ſpeake peculiarlie vnto you; yea, (to auoide offence) hearken all ye wiues, (or maidens that may bee wiues) eſpeciallie you that feare the Lord, and doe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19454:33"/> take his word to be your guide,<note place="margin">Neceſſarie things to be knovvne for the quiet of maried per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> if you doe deſire the happie life of Matrimonie, behold your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, know your place and ſtation, and who hath ſubiected you. If will and deſire be taken from you (touching rule and gouernment) what is left you to vſe of your owne authoritie? If therefore you will contend at law about ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie, you are bid lay down your intereſt, for God hath diſpoſed it vnto your husbands, not ſo much as to deſire any thing or doe any thing (as of your ſelues) but is made tributarie vnto your hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.<note place="margin">The ſhrewde wife ſaith this is hard.</note> And from hence (I take it) it came,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou. 19.13.</hi> Contention pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly aſcribed to the vvife by Salomon.</note> that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpake ſo much, and that ſo bitterly about the contentions of the wife, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them (as by a proper name) the <hi>Contentions</hi> of the wife; and her the contentious perſon, if there be any ſtrife, betweene her and her husband. Who, although he ſpake of diuers wicked men,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19454:34"/> and of diuers imperfections of men; yet neuer (ſpeaking of the husband) doth hee call it, the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands contention, but the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wife,<note place="margin">Prou. 27.15.</note> comparing her and her contentions to the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of an houſe or gutter: noting therby the poore huſbands miſery that is ſo matched with a conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious wife,<note place="margin">The poore huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands miſerie.</note> as if he ſtoode continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnder the dropping of an houſe: as alſo noting her diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereby, where he ſaith, that <hi>Hee which hideth her</hi> (or would ſeeme to couer ſuch infirmities) <hi>hideth the winde:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> that is, is like him that would goe about that, that were impoſſible; <hi>and ſhee is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as the oyle in his right hand that vttereth it ſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> which cannot bee concealed, though hee would neuer ſo faine. Heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie text;<note place="margin">Pro. 27.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>A continuall dropping in the day of raine, and a contentious woman are alike. Hee that hideth her, hideth the wind, and ſhe is as the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19454:34"/> oyle in his right hand, that vttereth it ſelfe.</hi> In another place thus hee hath it; <hi>A fooliſh ſonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19.13.</note> 
               <hi>is the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie of the father: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the wife, are like a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall dropping,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this you will obiect and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> ſay: May not the wife contend for lawfull and good things? May the wife doe nothing, but the husband may denie her? To theſe two queſtions thus I anſwere: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> (I cal them two, becauſe they are diuers and diſtinct.) Firſt, vndoubtedlie,<note place="margin">The vvife may not contend by any meanes. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is.</note> ſhe muſt not contend, no not for good things, that is, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by contending that braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, bickering, and vexing diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, whereby, as it were, ſhee will ſeeme to wreſtell and wage warre, for that which is wanting, through which, either ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth his patience, offendeth his loue, breaketh quiet peace, or reſiſteth his authoritie.</p>
            <p>Admit (you will ſay) it bee for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19454:35"/> moſt neceſſarie duties, as for good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the family, for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to bee performed, for reſtraint of euill exerciſes, or entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of godly friends, may ſhee not ſtriue for theſe things? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,<note place="margin">The wife may vſe perſwaſion, but not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> for theſe ſhe may intreate; for theſe ſhee may wiſely ſpeake and counſell; for the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe amiſſe, ſhee may moue friends to perſwade: but to fall out, to braule, to lower, to be ſullen and fret, or, (which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree worſe (as it is a note aboue <hi>Ela</hi>) to ſcold and ſpeake pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſlie,<note place="margin">A note aboue Ela.</note> this is beyond her place, it is intolerable contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The contrarie to which, is contained vnder thoſe wordes of the virtuous wiues expreſſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:<note place="margin">Prou. 31.26.</note> 
               <hi>She openeth her mouth with wiſedome, and the Law of grace, is in her tongue.</hi> To open her mouth with wiſedome, is not to braule, but to intreate her husband for things amiſſe to be redreſſed: and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19454:35"/> how contrarie is ſcolding &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious words to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Law of grace?</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, what if all <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> this preuaile not, may ſhe not yet contend? for anſwere, I ſay: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the caſe to be betweene thee and thy Prince: For reformation, or otherwiſe in withholding right, wilt thou trie him by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes in words or deedes? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of that,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.3.</note> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) For he will doe euen what hee liſt. I know the conditions are very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and vnequall in their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent degrees; yet this may be drawne out of the compariſon, that as there is no ſtriuing with a Prince, becauſe of his power; ſo there is (or ſhould be) no conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the husband (for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer cauſe) becauſe of that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſoueraigntie which is in his hand, hee will doe whatſoeuer hee liſt (lawfull, honeſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different) and ſhee cannot hinder him. So that looke how vaine a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19454:36"/> thing it is, for one to ſtriue with another, that is bound hand and foote, and cannot wagge a finger; ſo vaine a thing it is for the wife (who for euery thing muſt depend vpon her husbands will) to ſtriue and wreſtle with him. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the things which are to bee obtained or redreſſed, bee to bee done by him, and cannot be done by her,<note place="margin">The vvife diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, rather then by refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</note> the burthen being his and not hers (ſhe hauing done her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by intreatie) ſhe is diſcharged, and he ſtandeth guiltie: he being King, Prieſt, and Prophet in his houſe, he ſhall anſwere for it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </note>The other queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> [whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wife may doe nothing, but the husband may denie her] muſt be thus conſidered. If they be partely of the aforeſaid nature, things indifferent, he may forbid her; or things good and lawfull, being extraordinarie and not common duties of religion and Gods ſeruice, hee may reſtraine
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19454:36"/> her; but he doth euill (it may bee) in it, which is not the queſtion. My reaſon of which reſtraint (or authoritie) is this,<note place="margin">Numb. 30.9.</note> where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, that if a woman ſhall vow a vow vnto God, if her husband diſallow her the ſame, in the day that hee heareth it, hee ſhall make her vow that ſhe hath pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with her lippes, of no effect. As touching common &amp; ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie duties and partes of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeruice, as the hearing of his Word, Prayer, Sacraments, &amp; ſuch like, or ſhall command her things vnlawfull or vncomely, ſhe is not bound to obey herein, neither can he reſtraine her; or if hee ſhall do it by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhe is excuſed, as one violently hindred from her dutie, and he ſhall beare the ſinne: neither may the hazard of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, wrath, or offence,<note place="margin">The vvife muſt do ſome duties with hazard of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> be any iuſt excuſe, if violently ſhe be not hindred, touching the duties of Gods ſeruice, which with patience
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19454:37"/> ſhe is to beare, and ſubmit her ſelfe vnto. But in any caſe ſhee muſt not contend, for any cauſe or matter,<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of the wiues conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> which is no way to win, nor meanes to obtaine, but to breake peace &amp; vnitie, to diſſolue loue, and make way to al diſorder and diſcontented eſtate. This is the beſt fruite that can come of contention, with either wiſe or fooliſh man. If he be wiſe, he will not beare it, that is, not beare the loſing of his authoritie: If he be fooliſh, he will bee more intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and not endure it. Wiſelie therefore did <hi>Abigail</hi> in the caſe of her husbands danger;<note place="margin">Abigails wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> who (not conſulting with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was not in caſe) ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred rather in a good action to beare ſome blame, then to omit a needefull thing. Surely, if he had knowne it, it is probable hee would not haue conſented; which thing, becauſe ſhe feared &amp; knew he might reſtraine her will, ſhe did
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19454:37"/> it priuilie. So ſuch wiues, (as whoſe husbands are <hi>Nabals</hi>) haue onelie libertie to doe good without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to hazard blame. But that the husband may reſtraine if he be acquainted with their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and they muſt obey, there is no queſtion.</p>
            <p>Let the wife therefore by all meanes ſhun the obloquie of a contentious wife, wherein is ſo much diſhonour, as almoſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more. For what a ſhame is it to a wife, to be compared to a dropping houſe? or to haue a corner in a houſe top (for a man to liue alone in) yea, or the very wildernes to be preferred before her? therefore in the Prouerbes hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.9.19.</note> that <hi>It is better to dwell in the corner of the houſe top, then with a contentious woman in a wide houſe:</hi> And againe;<note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>It is better to dwell in the wildernes, then with a contentious and angrie woman.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A womans diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</note> Oh how ill beſeeming is it, the chaſte,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19454:38"/> ſober, modeſt, and amiable face of a louing and virtuous wife, to fret, lower, skowle, ſcold, braule, or bee vnquiet towards her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? if ſuch ſaw their faces then in a glaſſe, it would make them loue the practiſe of ſuch behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our the worſe for euer.</p>
            <p>On the contrarie ſide, if they did but know what fetters, bonds, and perſwaſions, their kind and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full behauiour were vnto verie fooliſh (much more to wiſe and godly) husbands, for obtaining of their willes, in things lawfull and neceſſarie, they would neuer fall into a contentious humor, but by kindnes ouercome.<note place="margin">A ſimilitude of the vvinde and the Sun.</note> The wind and the Sunne may be ſimilitudes, in this caſe to ſet forth the effect hereof. It is ſaid, they once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, who ſhould haue the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie to make a Traueller caſt off his cloke: the winde began (after his ruffling manner) to blow with ſtrength: then more ſtronglie: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19454:38"/> that with violence, as though he would carrie away man and all: but the more hee threatned, the faſter the ſaid traueller held his cloke about him, neither could the winde by his ruffling get vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie. The Sunne by warmth and faire demeanes, ſetteth vpon his taske; who, not at firſt preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, increaſed his warmth, till at length, not onely it cauſed him to caſt off his cloke, but his coate and doublet too. So verily, if wiues did know how vnſauorie their ruffling courſes of contentions are vnto husbands hearts,<note place="margin">Though kind and dutifull perſvvaſion vvill not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, yet muſt contention needes be the vvorſt, though by it ſhe ſhould preuaile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is no honeſt meane appointed of God. <hi>Mark 6.21. Heſt. 5.</hi>
               </note> and how much their amiable, louing, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient perſwaſions, are more likely (if ought at al) to take place with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only to get victorie of the cloke, but of coate and al, &amp; wiſely watching their times and ſeaſons (as <hi>Herodias</hi> did, though in a bad cauſe) but indeed as Queene <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> did in a better &amp; good cauſe) they would ſurely abhorre and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19454:39"/> their windie courſe, and wholly cleaue vnto the way of wiſedome. They are therefore more then fooliſh (for euen that name the Scripture giueth vnto indiſcreet both women and men) I ſay they are more then fooliſh women,<note place="margin">Iob. 2.10. Prou. 14.1.</note> that cannot ſay with themſelues, if I cannot obtaine by gentle and moderate meanes, I ſhall neuer preuaile by vnlawfull meanes: for verily contending is meerely vnlawful; not only (as I haue ſaid) an vnlikely, but an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull courſe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee (I truſt) this point moſt euident, that by no meanes the wife may contend, no not for things lawfull.<note place="margin">A wiſe mans ſaying, if wiues would beleeue it.</note> Well (as one ſaith) the cauſe of contention may be in the husband, but the fault of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, is ſurely in the wife. The husband may be fooliſh and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked (as <hi>Nabal</hi> was;) and therein giue occaſion (or cauſe) to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious nature, but the wife
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19454:39"/> muſt auoid it, as <hi>Abigail</hi> did, who wiſely preuented the euill, but brawled not for his follie. Let this rule be obſerued, and there ſhall be no contention.</p>
            <p>But when this aduice in the wife is no more regarded, (then in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it is) and that the order of Gods decree is ſo violated,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> is it any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, if there bee contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and wife? Nay rather it were a wonder, if there ſhould be peace: for whereas the Lord hath inueſted the husband with the authoritie and headſhip, will any loſe this authority, &amp; reſigne it prepoſterouſlie? will hee loſe his libertie, and caſt his ſcepter to the ground?<note place="margin">The vvife in vſurping au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as it is ſaid of S. Peter, vvith his heeles vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard.</note> will hee bee nailed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, with his heeles vpward? I denie not (much leſſe iuſtifie) the husband to be in cauſe oftentimes, of diſunitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, when he ſhall be careleſſe of neceſſarie and godlie duties, improuident, vnthriftie, froward,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19454:40"/> rigorous, and worſe then all this, yet ſtill (as hath been prooued) the contentions are the wiues, and the fault of contending will light on her vnanſwerablie, becauſe ſhe is ſubiected vnto a tributary eſtate, being made for the man, and hee made her head. She being the cauſe of all his miſerie,<note place="margin">VVhen hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands are fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard, vviues muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they vvere the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall cauſe thereof in them.</note> if ſhe beare any miſerie by meanes of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion, ſhee muſt looke vnto the originall thereof, which firſt ſprang in her ſelfe; whereas for a man to tranſgreſſe that hath the prerogatiue, and is, as it were, the king and chiefe gouernour of the familie, for him to ſay with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech</hi> (though I ſay not iuſtifiable) <hi>I would ſlay a man in my wound, and a young man in mine hurt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.23.</note> yet is it not ſo monſtrous or intollerable, or to be wondred at: though the dutie and beneuolence, thus (with <hi>Lamech</hi>) to terrifie, and feare the wife, bee thereby wounded and diſcouraged; yet is not the order
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19454:40"/> of Gods ordinance ſo inuerted and ouerthrowne as in the former diſobedience and contention of the wife.</p>
            <p>Al which, I ſpeake not to oppreſſe the wife, as ſhall appeare (my deare friend) in the matter ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and therefore doe I craue your patience vnto the very ende) but to enforce the euill of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, by diſcouering the cauſe and fault therof; that by wiſdome it may be preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, or with ſpeed remoued: which being abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (I meane the fault of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) in the wife, ſhe muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie take care to remoue it, or beare the blame thereof.</p>
            <p>Neither yet is it a vile eſtate, whereunto the wife is thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected (as partly hath bin ſhewed) (though her will and deſire bee both captiued) neither yet the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight way for her to relieue her ſelfe, if the burthen be too heauie to contend for eaſe: For, as the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19454:41"/> husband may lawfully (if he will) impart his authoritie with his wife, (which who ſo doth not is not wiſe, if his wife bee virtuous and fit to vſe it) ſo yet it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her to take the beſt courſe to obtaine and winne it. Now contending (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) is abſolutely denied her: what then may compaſſe it? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her ſubiection ſhall get her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,<note place="margin">True ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the right vvay to rule.</note> and her obedience rule; the more ſubiect, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power ſhall ſhee obtaine; and the more humble in her obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the more libertie ſhall ſhe win. If therefore there were not an euill ſpirit, &amp; a corrupt nature to blind the wife, rather with the wind to contend by force for her will, then patiently with the ſunne to gaine it by virtue and diligence, they might much more preuaile for rule and gouernment then by the warre of contention,<note place="margin">Contention conſumeth loue.</note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth loue. I will giue that by
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19454:41"/> intreatie, which by conſtraint I will not; and remit a debt,<note place="margin">Matth. 18.26.</note> if the debter craue patience, whereas if he be inſolent, he may rot in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it: why then do not wiues conſider this, that virtue, rather then violence, ſubmiſſion then contention, refuſing then vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, patience then ſtubbornnes, will more preuaile for peace in their fellowſhip, and libertie to their will, then al their croſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions can euince and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere? But what if no grace or virtue will preuaile? to whom then are they ſubiect, if the husband be vnreaſonable? is it vnto man, or vnto God? I ſay vnto God,<note place="margin">The threefold pledge: <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> To loue,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> To cheriſh,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> To obey.</item>
                  </list>
               </note>and vnto his ordinance, to whom ſhee ſweareth obedience in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage knot.</p>
            <p>Now out of all this (deare friend) I ſhall neede no great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation vnto you, to imbrace this wiſedome, ſeeing the courſe I preſcribe, is not onely the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19454:42"/> of the word of God, but in all ſenſe and reaſon both the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt the faithfulleſt, and moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable for the wife; yea, of both good and bad it is moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, except ſome rare woman for wickednes that excelleth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For, was there euer commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation giuen to <hi>Sarah,</hi> aboue her obedience? of whom the holie Ghoſt ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.6.</note> That ſhee <hi>obeyed her huſband, and called him Lord:</hi> whoſe meeke and quiete ſpirit (oppoſed to the contentious ſpirit) the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> is a thing much ſet by of God; Whoſe daughters (ſaith hee againe) yee are whiles yee do well,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> not being affraid with any terror. Or is there a more odious reproch vnto a wife (whoredome ſet aſide, which diſſolues the knot; how much more then when whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and contention are met in one?) I ſay, is there a more ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reproch vnto the wife, then to bee <hi>Salomons</hi> contentious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19454:42"/> of whom wee ſpake before?<note place="margin">Prou. 6.33.</note> there can be no greater (that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting blot excepted), for that it ouerthroweth the virtue of the wife; prooueth her to haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meeke nor quiet ſpirit, but froward, inſolent and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Which meeknes &amp; quietnes, if it be as the Apoſtle auouched, a thing of God ſo much ſet by, then needes muſt frowardnes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention bee vnto him moſt dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable; and ſo conſequently, that which is ſo odious to God, and ſo offenſiue to man (as to ſtand vnder the dropping of a gutter), muſt needes be a diuelliſh nature and a reprochfull qualitie.<note place="margin">Prou. 12.4.</note> But (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) the virtuous wife is a crowne to her husband, ſhee will doe him good and not euill,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.12.</note> and that not a day, or twaine, but, in an vnwearied courſe, all the daies of her life: giue her therefore the fruit of her hands, and let her owne workes praiſe her in the gates.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:19454:43"/>
            <p>Now in all the ſubiection that I haue ſpoken of in the wife, I haue meant no ſeruil ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or dutie, but dutie with a kind of equalitie, and equalitie with reuerence. For the dutie,<note place="margin">Obedience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to degree.</note> or word of obedience is very large and generall, and muſt bee conſidered according to his degree. There is the ſeruants du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; the ſons dutie, and the wiues dutie. The ſonnes differeth from the ſeruants dutie, becauſe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant abideth not in the houſe for euer, whereas the ſonne (being heire) ſhall inherit and abide. His obedience is with loue, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants with feare. The wiues dutie (or obedience) alſo differeth from the ſonnes, and is by degree more excellent, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is graced and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with a kind of equalitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fellow heires (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) or heires together of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Ghoſt there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth honour, (as to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker veſſell) that is, by honour hee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19454:43"/> meaneth tender regard, as not to prouoke, or diſcourage, but as a veſſell (ſo profitable for vſe) and as the weaker veſſell, ſo with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be gouerned. And this putteth a difference alſo, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the ſonnes obedience, in boldnes, in kindnes and in equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.4.</note> The husband (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) hath not power ouer himſelf, but the wife: ſo then the wiſe hath that intereſt, in, and ouer the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, (the faithfull and dutifull wife I meane) which neither the ſeruant nor ſon can require, nor the husband impart with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Hitherto (you will ſay) I haue wholly, as it were, intreated of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dutie of the wife. And you will further ſay, I haue laid loade vpon their ſhoulders, who are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker veſſels, longing, it may be, to heare the dutie of the husband in like ſort ſet forth, to ſee what bonds he is to bee tied withall in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19454:44"/> his conuerſation to his wife. It is true, that the further our duties are diſcouered vnto vs, the more grieuous and tedious it doth ſeeme vnto vs; each delighting to heare rather the others dutie, then their owne and proper dutie; the husband is pleaſed when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiues dutie is extended to the vttermoſt, and the wife likewiſe, when the husbands is enlarged;<note place="margin">Jt is a good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a good ſpirit to delight in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing of our ovvne duties eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</note> but this is no good ſigne either of a good husband, or a virtuous wife. The better husband, the more hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to ſee and vnderſtand, both the properties of the good husband, that hee may the better follow them, and the qualities of the bad husband, that he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid them: The good wife like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hath her eyes bent to the things that may be excellent, that her obedience may bee perfect, caring altogether what is her owne dutie, and not what is her husbands. For whiles men and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19454:44"/> women are thus intent, and doe caſt their eies on others, rather then vpon themſelues, it is not poſſible they ſhould be ſo careful of their owne duties as they ought to bee. Let the wife therefore deſire nothing of the knowledge of her husbands, but of her owne, nor the husband of his wiues duty, but of his owne; nor any man of his neighbours du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but of his owne.<note place="margin">That is, not ſimplie, but in compariſon.</note> Thinke it too long that thou heareſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans dutie deſcribed, and thine owne deferred, and delight in the inlarging of thine owne, and with the ſight of thy defects, that thou maiſt abound in the knowledge of thine owne obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and leaue other mens bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to their owne ſhoulders. Oh, ſay ſome,<note place="margin">Vaine mens profiting.</note> (when they haue heard a ſermon), ſuch a note tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſuch a man to the quick, he was not better met withall a good while. But not a word touched
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19454:45"/> himſelfe, for that he let ſlip &amp; flee ouer his head, as an arrow ſhot beyond him. This is not well, that we caſt the wallet of our own ſins behind vs, and hang other mens ſins before; look vnto other mens duties, and neglect our owne.</p>
            <p>But that I haue ſomewhat ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vpon this point, of the cauſe of contention betweene man and wife, or laid forth the wiues dutie of ſubiection &amp; obedience ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what largely, hath not been to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the wife, or to put a ſword into the hand of the husband to vpbraid his wife with her dutie; but partly to informe all godly and virtuous wiues,<note place="margin">All good wiues deſire to know their duties to the vttermoſt.</note> what is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or diſhonorable in them, which none that are virtuous, but doe deſire to ſee; and principally to lay a ſound foundation for the husband to build vpon. Which being thus laid, you ſhall now ſee what the building will ariſe to be.</p>
            <p>Certainly, it cannot but be a moſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19454:45"/> ſtrong attractiue, and effectuall meane, to draw from the husband,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.3.</note> that due beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which Gods word enioyneth him, were hee a very <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.</note> much more (an <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanah</hi>) an husband of wiſedome and vnderſtanding. We reade of no contention betweene <hi>Nabal</hi> and <hi>Abigail;</hi> though hee were ſaid (and doubtleſſe not without cauſe both by his ſeruants and his wife (ſhee being eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by his owne ſafetie to ſay it) being ſaid (I ſay) to be ſo chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and wicked,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.17.</note> that one could not ſpeake vnto him: the cauſe, or reaſon whereof, is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to bee in the virtue and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his wife: who obſeruing his nature, and waighing her own place, tooke alwaies opportunitie of time to contriue her affaires. When ſhe had met <hi>Dauid,</hi> and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified his wrath, did ſhe preſentlie runne with hue and crie vnto her husband? did ſhe charge him
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19454:46"/> with his folly, and churliſh nature? you know ſhe did not, but waited till hee were fit to bee enformed thereof.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.36.</note> The very text ſaith, that when ſhe came to the feaſt, and found him ſo well tipled and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſhe told him nothing, more or leſſe, not one word or inkeling (as wee ſay) vntill the morning. And what then? onely ſhe related the danger, without note of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe or contention, onely to make him (as I conceiue) the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer againſt another time.<note place="margin">A note to be remembred.</note> And ſurelie it were a very gratious and godlie care both in wiues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their husbands, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againe in husbands towards their wiues, to obſerue and waigh the natures each of other; and to take opportunitie and fitnes of time to ſpeake each to other of ſuch things, as each would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at others hands. If the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be of an angrie or cholerick nature, is it any more for the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19454:46"/> wife, then to beare, as it were, a flaſh of heate? which, when the husband obſerueth (as verily hee is a foole that could or would not note ſuch a virtue in his wife) it would not onely be a meane the more ſpeedily to quench y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heate, but to make double ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward with loue &amp; kindnes. But if in the heate and flame ſhe ſhall powre in her oyle of frowardneſſe and contention, in ſtead of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of patience and pacification, is it any meruaile or wonder, if the houſe be ſet on fire?</p>
            <p>The husband alſo muſt not diſdaine to bee counſelled by his wife, to heare her reaſons, and to waigh her words.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.9.</note> For ſhe is giuen for an helper, two are better then one; &amp; God (many times) reueales that to the wife, that hee doth not to the husband.<note place="margin">Gen. 21.12.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Sarah</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael;</hi> he was bid of the Lord to giue eare vnto her. And
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19454:47"/> did not <hi>Manoahs</hi> wife ſtrengthen him, after the ſight of the Angell and the ſacrifice which he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, who feared that they ſhould die becauſe they had ſeene the Lord? which feare ſhe put away with a moſt wiſe reaſon, ſaying: <hi>If the Lord would kill vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>he would not haue receiued a burnt offering, and a meate offering at our hands; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would hee haue ſhewed vs all theſe things, nor would haue told vs any ſuch,</hi> &amp;c. And what is that honour that S.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of, which the husband (being a man of vnderſtanding) ſhould giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wife, but (amongſt other things) regard vnto her aduice? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies prouided that ſhee counſell not as did <hi>Iobes</hi> wife,<note place="margin">Iob. 2.9.</note> to bleſſe God and die: nor with <hi>Michol</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine at his zeale, and godlines; but counſelling wiſely, ſhe is as a counſeller to be heard and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Neither commeth <hi>Salomons</hi> counſell ſhort of this, when hee
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19454:47"/> biddeth the husband to giue his virtuous wife the fruite of her hands, that is, being wiſe, virtuous and prouident, let her bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended &amp; truſted for ſuch a wife. And put caſe there bee not to bee found all thoſe abſolute qualities of that virtuous wife, in her whom thou haſt choſen to bee thy wife, but ſome infirmities,<note place="margin">A rule for the husband to beare with the wiues infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> (yea many infirmities,) to beare with hers (as it becommeth the wiſe husband to doe) conſider thine owne that ſhe muſt, and doth beare with in thee: if thine be more then hers, thou canſt not bee grieued to beare hers; if hers bee more then thine, ſhe is ſaid to bee the weaker veſſell, and thou the ſtronger, that the bigger horſe might beare the heauier loade.<note place="margin">Beare with the homelines of the ſimilitude.</note> Why hath God made thee the ſtronger but to beare the frailties and infirmities of thy wife? for a man the wiues, or a wife the husbands, for either (I meane) to diſcouer others infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19454:48"/> (by way of reproch) is the greateſt reproch that can fall to either. Except it be in ſuch a caſe, as wherein <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith her cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions cannot be hid:<note place="margin">Prou. 27.16.</note> but <hi>He that would hide them, hideth the wind, and ſhe is as oyle in his right hand that vttereth it ſelfe.</hi> The husband muſt dwell with his wife as a man of vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> that is, as one that hath vnderſtanding ſo to gouerne, that hee giue not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion by fooliſhnes to be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor by ouermuch ſeueritie to be hated or feared.</p>
            <p>That care, which before I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that the husband and wife ſhould duely marke each others diſpoſition and nature, ought eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to begin betimes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For (if for want thereof) they fall once vnto contention, and each by contention, to take diſlike of other, it will grow (without great grace) in either, or both, vnto hardnes of heart; and then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19454:48"/> kind of marking each others nature will enſue: Namely, not to preuent euill or contention, but to deuiſe euill and contention; and ſo this counſell and remedie come to late.<note place="margin">Prou. 17.14.</note> Therefore doth <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> giue this counſell, where he compareth the beginning of ſtrife to bee like one that openeth the waters, that is, maketh a breach in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a banke or bay of waters; therefore ſaith he, <hi>Or euer conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be medled with, leaue off.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> If this doe hold in common contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and of any nature, much more in this ciuill and houſehold ſtrife. It is wiſedome ſometimes to ſeeme guiltie in ſome cauſe,<note place="margin">Great vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſeeme guiltie ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a ſeaſon, vvhere one is guiltles.</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wife towards the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or the husband towards the wife, during the time of wrath, if it bee once kindled or inflamed, and to pacifie rather by intreating then excuſing or cleering: for which, opportunitie of time ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but afterward be found to cleare,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19454:49"/> and which cannot but be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to bee done by great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A ſpeciall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</note>It is certainelie a great encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of the wife, where the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band maketh his loue to appeare by ſound effects: ſhewing that he regardeth her dutie, obſerueth her labour, pitieth her paines, conſidereth her weakenes, and would lighten her yoke and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, by any meanes he could; that he truſteth her, and is not lightly or vniuſtly iealous of her: not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting too narrow an account of her domeſticall affaires, but as if ſhe were himſelfe, who is indeede become one with himſelf, his half ſelf or other ſelf; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of her trueth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">Prou. 31.29.</note> 
               <hi>Many daughters haue done virtuouſlie, but thou</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) ſurmounteſt them all:</hi> There the husband obſerueth the labors, trauails, night-watchings, and early riſings of his wife, which
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19454:49"/> were ſpoken of before) and laſtlie doth crowne, and commend them in her. The contrarie neglecting of all the poore wiues trauaile, taketh away her heart, breedeth diſcontentment, &amp; maketh weake her hands: and for either the wife ouer the husband, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> husband o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the wife, to be attainted with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> filthy ſin of iealouſie,<note place="margin">Beware of cauſeleſſe iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie.</note> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next way to cauſe either to fall into the ſin.</p>
            <p>It is an hard taske, to meete with all the inconueniences of the marriage ſtate, or to applie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions to all the euills that may be feared therein, which S. <hi>Pauls</hi> wordes imported, when (hauing ſaid, <hi>[ſuch ſhall haue tribulation in the fleſh]</hi> he added withall, <hi>but I ſpare you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.28.</note> I ſpare to relate all the dangers that I could. But ſurely <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt principall meane to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent them, is the obſeruing of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdinance of God: and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all cauſe of euill vnto man and wife, is, (as hath bin ſaid) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19454:50"/> of the ſame. If the husband rule with loue, and the wiſe obey with cheerefulnes, and either of them be contented with their lot &amp; portion in each other, then muſt the yoke needs go eaſie. But if the wife will vſurpe, and not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her head &amp; king, or will not vſe the fitteſt meanes for her rule and libertie; or hauing what ſhee would, cannot (or will not) vſe it to her husbands honor, &amp; thus lay a foundation of contention and ſtrife, Gods wiſedome is deſpiſed, it cannot be well.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I doe exhort you both (as my moſt deere friends, whom as I daily pray for, ſo would I bee glad to ſee the fruits of my prayers in the happines of your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) I ſay, I doe exhort you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe mutual duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne you both. You (Miſtris <hi>Lucie</hi>) to wiſe ſubiection, to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and Chriſtian reuerence, to faithfull and dutifull obedience:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19454:50"/> which ſhall not onely bee your crowne of glorie amongſt the godly wiſe, as it was <hi>Sarahs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation by the holy Ghoſt to be obedient to her husband; but if you deſire to rule and to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with all your husband hath, this is the way, and there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If you thus ſay, giue me the ſword, you ſhall haue both it, and all aſſiſtance to vſe it; but if you will ſtriue to wreſt it out of your husbands hand, you will not only miſſe your deſire, but take hurt by ſtriuing. Thus your godly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection ſhal gaine you more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, eaſe, honour, and lawfull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, then all the contention in the world can bring to paſſe: and hate both the name and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a contentious wife; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſhee is, as an incureable dropping, and intollerable. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to rule a familie with the husbands aſſignement, is a great honour to the wife: but to beare
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19454:51"/> ſway againſt his will and fauour, no greater ſhame. Such wiues are ſcoffed at, as their husbands ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; ſuch husbands eſteemed but vnwiſe and fooliſh.</p>
            <p>And you (Maſter <hi>Geruoyſe</hi>) as my deere friend, I counſell vnto the vnderſtanding of a man of wiſedome.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> Know your wife to be a veſſell, therefore neceſſarie; I wil not ſay (as one ſaith) a neceſſarie euill, for I truſt ſhee ſhall bee that virtuous wife, that ſhall doe her husband good and not euill, al the daies of her life; but I doubt not to ſay, a neceſſarie veſſell for fruit vnto Gods glorie; a veſſell, when you are full of ſorrowes, to helpe beare them, and eaſe you. A veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, to containe your counſels, and inſtructions,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.18.</note> &amp; not to be plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, by any aduerſarie, but as a faithfull bulwarke againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. Yet being withall the weaker veſſell, ſhee muſt bee ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered accordingly. Our moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19454:51"/> veſſels, (whether glaſſe or gold) are commonly the weakeſt, by reaſon, either of nature, or workemanſhip, &amp; thoſe we moſt preciſely order, not roughly, or careleſſely. To a virtuous woman, there is no veſſell, no iewell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable; count her therefore the cheefeſt veſſell in your houſe that muſt containe your ſelfe and all your treaſures. Her price,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.10.</note> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> is aboue the pearles; ſhew not your rough and manlike cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage (like <hi>Lamech</hi>) to your wife, but to your enemie. You are both but one, therefore be both but as one. Looke not ſo much what is required of her, as what is due to her from your ſelfe.<note place="margin">Gen. 20.16.</note> You are the couering of her eies, which muſt defend her, not oppreſſe her. She is of godly, wiſe, and worſhipfull ſtocke and parentage; her yeeres haue been ſeaſoned hitherto with the ſalt of godly education; and therefore the fitter for your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19454:52"/> to worke vpon; make you the worke perfect, and you ſhall haue both the honour and the comfort of the worke. To bee briefe, what is wanting in her, (yeeres being conſidered) that may derogate from the title of a virtuous wife? this I ſpeake to you, not to her, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhing my words to be eſteemed as farre from flattery, as mine heart is from hypocriſie in that I ſpeake. You are both in the fitteſt time to begin an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie eſtate; lay therefore the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation according to Gods holie word, and the building ſhall bee glorious. Let that be the rule of both your duties, and know that God is moſt wiſe in directing both your ſtates.</p>
            <p>Thus whiles you both regard the duties of your ſeuerall places, ioyntly towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord firſt, then mutually towards one another, how eaſie will the burthen of your familie and callings be vnto you?
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19454:52"/> the equal draught, maketh y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen light. What an example will <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be to ſeruants, to children, to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eighbours, to friends, yea to all <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, to be followed &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed? So that,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.33.</note> you firſt ſeeke the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingdom of heauen and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eouſnes therof, the glorie of your God, in a religious profeſſion of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is name, all other things, (as wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, vnderſtanding, riches, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue pleaſures) ſhall bee caſt vpon <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou. You ſhall be moſt happie firſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this preſent life, &amp; more happie <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boue happines in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life to come. Which is the ſcope of this my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender labour and dutie vnto you <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth: ſlender I call it, for ſo it is: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd my dutie I doe acknowledge <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for diuers cauſes which I will <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I profeſſe euer plainenes and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, not eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or deep know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge in any of my writings. And <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o I commend you both to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efit of all inſtruction, and al vnto Gods glory in Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
